Jonathan Krause Rare Newspaper and Magazine Collection 1648-1881 E302.1 .J76 E302.1 .J76
Lilly Library
- 19th Century American Topics
  - Louisiana Territory and Purchase
    - MEMORIAL ON LOUISIANA BY ROBERT LIVINGSTON, MINISTER TO FRANCE, The Balance, July 19, 26, August 2, 9, 1803; Size: Small (Item 655)
    - ESSAY ON LOUISIANA, The Balance, August 16, 23, 30, September 6, 13, 20, 27, 1803; Size: Small (Item 656)
    - TREATY ON LOUISIANA BETWEEN FRANCE AND THE UNITED STATES (LOUISIANA PURCHASE), The Balance, November 1, 8, 1803; Size: Small (Item 657)
    - ACTIONS OF AND CONSEQUENCES FOR SPAIN, The Balance, November 1, 8, 1803; Size: Small (Item 658)
    - MESSAGE BY JEFFERSON AND THE RATIFICATION OF TREATY, The Balance, November 8, 1803; Size: Small (Item 659)
    - BILL ON LOUISIANA AND NEW ENGLAND RESERVATIONS ON PURCHASE AND AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE POSSESSION OF LOUISIANA AND SENATOR GRISWOLD SPEECH ON LOUISIANA AND REFERENCE TO JEFFERSON PROCLAMATION ON LOUISIANA AND EXPECTED RESISTANCE OF SPAIN TO TAKEOVER OF LOUISIANA, The Balance, November 15, 1803; Size: Small (Item 660)
    - COMPARISON OF JAY AND LOUISIANA TREATIES AND RESPONSE TO GRISWOLD SPEECH, The Balance, November 22, 29, December 6, 1803; Size: Small (Item 661)
    - CONCERNING SECRET APPROPRIATION TO PURCHASE LOUISIANA, New York Evening Post, November 30, 1803 (Item 662)
    - ESSAYS ON LOUISIANA, The Balance, December 6, 13, 20, 27, 1803; Size: Small (Item 663)
      Boundaries, physical description, inhabitants, laws.
    - DEARBORN LETTER AND NEW ORLEANS, The Balance, December 6, 20, 1803; Size: Small (Item 664)
    - PROCLAMATION OF FRENCH GOVERNOR IN NEW ORLEANS, New York Evening Post, January 2, 1804 (Item 665)
    - SPANISH LETTER, The Balance, February 5, 1805; Size: Small (Item 666)
    - MONROE MEETS WITH NAPOLEON ON LOUISIANA, The Balance, February 12, 1805; Size: Small (Item 667)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, April 30, May 28, July 9, August 27, 1805; Size: Small (Item 668)
    - RUMORS OF NEGROES ARMING IN NEW ORLEANS, The Balance, November 5, 1805; Size: Small (Item 669)
    - INHABITANTS OF LOUISIANA WANT WAR WITH SPAIN, The Balance, November 26, 1805; Size: Small (Item 670)
  - Missouri Compromise
    - DEBATES, EVENTS AND ACTIVITIES, Niles Weekly Register, March 4, July 22, September 23, 1820; Size: Small (Item 884)
  - Reconstruction Period
    - PRESIDENT JOHNSON'S RACIST VETO OF FREEDMEN'S BILL AND RANTING AND PARANOID SPEECH TALKING OF PRO-BLACK RADICAL REPUBLICANS AS TRAITORS AND ASSASSINS AND COMPARING HIMSELF TO CHRIST AND WILLING TO UNDERGO MARTYRDOM, New York Times, February 23, 1866 (Item 786)
      See Andrew Johnson 786
    - PRESIDENT JOHNSON'S RACIST VETO OF CIVIL RIGHTS BILL, New York Times, March 28, 1866 (Item 787)
      See Andrew Johnson 787
    - PROCLAMATION ON THE END OF THE CONFEDERATE INSURRECTION (CIVIL WAR), The World (New York), April 3, 1866 (Item 1052)
    - PRESIDENT JOHNSON'S RACIST AND DEFAMATORY CAMPAIGN SPEECHES, New York Herald, September 10, 1866 (Item 788)
      See Andrew Johnson 788
    - PRESIDENT JOHNSON'S RACIST AND DEFAMATORY CAMPAIGN SPEECHES, New York Times, September 13, 1866 (Item 789)
      See Andrew Johnson 789
    - PRESIDENT JOHNSON'S VETO OF THE FIRST RECONSTRUCTION ACT, New York Times, March 4, 1867 (Item 1053)
    - PRESIDENT JOHNSON'S RACIST VETO OF SUPPLEMENTARY RECONSTRUCTION BILL, New York Times, March 24, 1867 (Item 790)
      See Andrew Johnson 790
    - PROCLAMATION RESTORING ALL RIGHTS TO REBELLION PARTICIPANTS, New York Weekly Tribune, September 11, 1867 (Item 1054)
    - JOHNSON STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, The World, December 3, 1867 (Item 791)
      See Andrew Johnson 791
    - LETTER TO CONGRESSMAN MORRIS REGARDING THE INFAMOUS GENERAL ORDER NO. 11 WHICH LINCOLN RESCINDED, AND LETTER OF ADOLPH MOSES, New York Times, November 30, 1868 (Item 776)
      See Ulysses S. Grant 776
    - PROCLAMATION BY PRESIDENT GRANT SUSPENDING HABEAS CORPUS AND SOUTH CAROLINA KU KLUX KLAN, New York Times, October 18, 1871 (Item 1055)
      See Ulysses S. Grant 1055
    - EFFECTS OF MARTIAL LAW IN SOUTH CAROLINA AND COURTS OF GEORGIA, New York Times, October 22, 1871 (Item 1056)
  - Thirteenth Amendment
    - THE PASSAGE BY THE SENATE OF THE AMENDMENT TO ABOLISH SLAVERY AS PUBLISHED IN THE LEADING NEWSPAPER OF THE CONFEDERACY, Daily Richmond Examiner, May 4, 1864 (Item 1075)
      This was the historic first step. The radical Republicans in the House of Representatives had tried and failed to successfully pass the amendment. A second vote four months later was closer but still unsuccessful. The abolitionists failed to get a two-thirds majority. It would happen only after Lincoln's re-election in January 1865. The ratification by the states took almost another year but the final process concluded on December 6, 1865.
    - ABOLITION OF SLAVERY, Newark Daily Advertiser, January 10, February 1, 1865 (Item 885)
  - War of 1812
    - SPEECH OF TECUMSEH ON EVE OF BATTLE OF THAMES, Columbian Centinel, November 17, 1813 (Item 743)
      One of the most famous speeches by a Native American in history.
    - CAPTURE AND DESTRUCTION OF WASHINGTON, D.C., Weekly Messenger, September 2, 1814 (Item 744)
    - MADISON PROCLAMATION ON BURNING OF WASHINGTON, D.C., Weekly Aurora, September 13, 1814 (Item 745)
      See: James Madison 461
    - BATTLE OF NEW ORLEANS AND TREATY OF GHENT, Weekly Aurora, February 14, 1815 (Item 746)
      Includes Andrew Jackson 779
- 18th and 19th Century International Individuals and Topics
  - Catherine the Great
    - LETTER TO DE BROGLIE DEFENDING MONARCHY, Columbian Centinel, February 22, 1792 (Item 887)
  - French Revolution
    - LETTER FROM LOUIS ON CONSTITUTION AND RIGHTS OF MAN, Gazette of the United States, November 25, 1789 (Item 935)
    - LOUIS AND MARIE ATTEMPT TO FLEE FRANCE AND THEIR CAPTURE AND SUBSEQUENT DECLARATIONS, New York Journal and Patriotic Register, August 27, 1791 (Item 936)
    - LETTER FROM LOUIS OFFERING MONEY TO POOR, National Gazette, December 8, 1791 (Item 937)
    - LETTER FROM LOUIS ON FRENCH CONSTITUTION, National Gazette, March 8, 1792 (Item 938)
    - MARSHAL LUCKNER AND GEBERAL ROCHAMBEAU AND ANTI-PRIEST LEGISLATION AND GREAT BETRAYAL AND RETREAT AT MONS AND AUSTRIAN MANIFESTO AGAINST FRANCE, National Gazette, July 18, 1792 (Item 939)
    - AUSTRIAN MANIFESTO AND SUPRESSION OF RELIGIOUS ORGANIZATIONS IN FRANCE, National Gazette, July 21, 1792 (Item 940)
    - SPEECH BY LOUIS ON PUBLIC TRANQUILITY, Gazette of the United States, September 26, 1792 (Item 941)
      See: James Monroe 471
    - LOUIS ATTACKED AND SWISS GUARDS SLAUGHTERED AND PALACE OFFICIALS KILLED AND TRIAL FOR LOUIS, National Gazette, October 10, 1792 (Item 942)
    - DECLARATION OF DUKE OF BRUNSWICK DEMANDING RESTITUTION OF LOUIS AND CONDEMNING ATROCITIES, National Gazette, January 5, 1793 (Item 944)
      See: Federalists versus Republicans 679
    - LOUIS IS GUILLOTINED, Gazette of the United States, March 27, 1793 (Item 945)
      See: James Madison 446
    - SERVILE LETTER FROM POPE TO FRENCH ASSEMBLY ON MURDER OF PAPAL REPRESENTATIVE, National Gazette, May 4, 1793 (Item 946)
      See: Federalists versus Republicans 680
    - LAFAYETTE'S CRIMES AND GENERAL DUMOURIER LETTER TO CONVENTION ON ARMY FAILURE AND CONDORCET ON LOUIS TRIAL, National Gazette, May 18, 1793 (Item 947)
      See: Federalists versus Republicans 681
    - GENERAL DUMOURIER WANTS TO PUT YOUNG LOUIS ON THRONE AND DUMOURIER'S INTENTIONS, National Gazette, June 1, 1793 (Item 948)
      See: Federalists versus Republicans 682
    - ON DUMOURIER AND LETTER ON DUMOURIER BY PRINCE COBOURG AND LETTER TO FRENCH BY COBOURG AND LETTER FROM DUMOURIER TO THE FRENCH, National Gazette, June 5, 1793 (Item 949)
      See: Federalists versus Republicans 683
    - DUMOURIER LETTER TO THE FRENCH, National Gazette, June 8, 1793 (Item 950)
      See: Federalists versus Republicans 684
    - PROCLAMATION OF DUMOURIER AND LETTER OF GENERAL DAMPIERRE AND DUMOURIER ESCAPE AND ARREST OF MARAT, National Gazette, June 12, 1793 (Item 951)
    - DECLARATION OF THE RIGHTS OF MAN AND CITIZEN 1793, Columbian Centinel, September 7, 1793 (Item 1076)
      It preceded the country's first republican constitution. Officially adopted, it never went into effect. The difference between this document and the 1789 Declaration of the Rights of Man is the stress on equality in the 1793 version, including new rights, and revisions to prior ones: to work, to public assistance, to education, and to resist oppression. It was written by the Jacobins after they had expelled the Girondists, and did not fully express their radicalism. Along with the 1789 document, it was one of the first great political statements on the need for human rights and dignity concerning the individual.
      Also contains JEFFERSON CIRCULAR TO MERCHANTS AS SECRETARY OF STATE, regarding plundering by privateers sponsored by England and France
    - SPEECH OF ROBESPIERRE ON ENEMIES OF FRANCE, Columbian Centinel, August 16, 1794 (Item 953)
      See: George Washington 589
  - The Jacobite Rebellion
    - THE SPEECH OF PHILIP LORD HARDWICKE, LORD HIGH-CHANCELLOR OF GREAT BRITAIN, AGAINST WILLIAM EARL OF KILMARNOCK, GEORGE EARL OF CROMARTIE, AND ARTHUR LORD BALMORINO AT THEIR TRIAL FOR TREASON IN AIDING PRINCE CHARLES EDWARD STUART, Edinburgh Evening Courant, August 14, 1746; Size: Small (Item 992)
      Comments from Mr. Krause: After the Battle of Culloden, the last pitched-battle fought on English soil, the spark of Scottish independence is doused forever, along with the clan system, various traditions, and any lingering Stuart sympathies. While the Duke of Cumberland commits atrocities in the Highlands, Charles, on the run, escapes to France and remains in exile.
  - Karl Marx
    - DISPATCH FROM LONDON AS FOREIGN CORRESPONDENT FOR HORACE GREELEY'S THE NEW YORK DAILY TRIBUNE, The New York Daily Tribune, May 15, 1854 (Item 1004)
      Comments from Mr. Krause: It is historically ironic that Marx always looked kindly on America and felt Russia was unalterably backward, given their stances toward his ideas. In the early 1850s, Marx was living in poverty with his family in London, mainly existing on handouts from Engels. Marx had done some sporadic journalism, and maybe occasionally got paid. But a job with The Daily Tribune would mean an income, however small. It was an anti-slavery paper with the largest circulation in America, a welcome platform to possibly disseminate Marx's and Engels' political philosophy, if it came to that. The future bugbear of capitalism would write to Engels in 1862, "If only I knew how to start some sort of business! All theory, dear friend, is grey, and only business green." While Marx had published The Communist Manifesto in 1848, an English edition would not appear for another forty years. Das capital appeared in the 1890's. America would barely know Marx during his lifetime.
  - Napoleon Bonaparte
    - LETTER TO DJEZZAR (BUTCHER) PASHA, OTTOMAN GOVERNOR OF ACRE, DURING MIDDLE EAST CAMPAIGN (1798-99), The Massachusetts Spy, September 25, 1799 (Item 1059)
      Napoleon threatened to march against the fortress city of Acre if Djezzar didn't support him against other Islamist groups. The day of the letter, Napoleon ordered the slaughter of 4000 Muslim prisoners from Djezzar's army after the siege of Jaffa. Djezzar declined to support Napoleon, who marched on Acre, suffering his first defeat, ruining his ambition to crown himself the new "white" Sultan, failing to take India from the British, and ultimately being pushed out of the Middle East altogether. At Acre, 600 years before, Richard the Lionheart had slaughtered 3000 Muslim prisoners during the Third Crusade.
    - PROCLAMATION ON SANTO DOMINGO, New England Palladium, March 16, 1802 (Item 888)
      See: Toussaint Louverture 425
    - IN SYRIA AND PALESTINE, The Balance, May 11, 1802; Size: Small (Item 889)
    - PROCLAMATION RESTORING ROMAN CATHOLIC RELIGION, The Balance, June 8, 1802; Size: Small (Item 890)
    - ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH, The Balance, June 15, 1802; Size: Small (Item 891)
    - MESSAGE TO THE PEOPLEAND ELECTION AS CONSUL, Columbian Centinel, July 3, 1802 (Item 892)
      Reference to Toussaint by name by Napoleon.
      See: Toussaint Louverture 428
    - SLAVERY TO BE MAINTAINED IN THE COLONIES AND NAPOLEON APPOINTED COUNCIL FOR LIFE, The Balance, July 13, 1802; Size: Small (Item 893)
    - DEBATE ON ASSASSINATION ATTEMPTS, The Balance, July 27, 1802; Size: Small (Item 894)
    - PLOT TO ASSASSINATE NAPOLEON, Farmer's Museum, August 10, 1802 (Item 895)
    - PROCLAMATION TO THE MUSLIMS ON LANDING IN EGYPT AND DESCRIPTION OF HIS PRIVATE LIFE, New York Herald, August 21, 1802 (Item 896)
      See: Anti-Jefferson 327
    - NAPOLEON AND THE VATICAN AND PORTRAIT OF NAPOLEON AND HIS ELECTION AS FIRST CONSUL AND SPEECH TO FRENCH SENATE, New York Herald, September 29, 1802 (Item 897)
      See: Anti-Jefferson 335
    - FRENCH CONSTITUTION, New York Herald, October 2, 1802 (Item 898)
    - LETTER TO SENATE AND FRENCH CONSTITUTION, The Balance, October 4, 1802; Size: Small (Item 899)
    - SPEECH TO THE SENATE ON BEING ELECTED CONSUL FOR LIFE, Farmer's Museum, October 5, 1802 (Item 900)
      See: Anti-Jefferson 338
    - FRENCH CONSTITUTION, The Balance, October 12, 19, 1802; Size: Small (Item 901)
    - RESPONSE TO THE ITALIAN ASSEMBLY AND RESTORATION OF CHRISTIAN HOLIDAYS, Farmer's Museum, October 12, 1802 (Item 902)
      See: Anti-Jefferson 341
    - LETTER TO DEY OF ALGIERS, The Balance, November 2, 1802; Size: Small (Item 903)
    - NAPOLEON'S ADMINISTRATION, Boston Gazette, November 25, 29, 1802 (Item 904)
      See: Thomas Paine 507 (November 25) and Anti-Paine 525 (November 29)
    - NAPOLEON IN SYRIA, The Balance, April 5, 1803; Size: Small (Item 905)
    - NAPOLEON AND BRITISH, The Balance, May 10, 1803; Size: Small (Item 906)
    - NEUTRALS MUST TAKE SIDES, The Balance, July 5, 1803; Size: Small (Item 907)
    - AS CONSUL AND NEGOTIATIONS WITH BOURBONS, The Balance, September 20, 1803; Size: Small (Item 908)
    - PLOTS AGAINST BONAPARTE, The Balance, October 11, 18, 1803; Size: Small (Item 909)
    - COMPARISON OF NAPOLEON AND LOUIS XVIII, The Balance, November 8, 15, 1803; Size: Small (Item 910)
    - EXCHANGE OF LETTERS BETWEEN MADAME BONAPARTE AND MADAME MOREAU ON FATE OF GENERAL MOREAU, Boston Gazette, August 16, 1804 (Item 911)
    - PROFESSIONS OF PEACE, The Balance, March 12, 1805; Size: Small (Item 912)
    - LETTER TO KING OF ENGLAND PROPOSING PEACE, The Balance, April 16, 1805; Size: Small (Item 913)
    - CORONATION, The Balance, May 28, 1805; Size: Small (Item 914)
    - PREPARATIONS FOR INVASION OF ENGLAND, The Balance, October 1, 22, 29, 1805; Size: Small (Item 915)
    - EUROPEAN TURMOIL AND ALIGNMENTS, The Balance, November 5, 12, 19, 26, 1805; Size: Small (Item 916)
    - SPEECH TO SENATE, The Balance, November 26, 1805; Size: Small (Item 917)
    - DECLARATION OF WAR AGAINST AUSTRIA AND RUSSIA, The Balance, December 10, 1805; Size: Small (Item 918)
    - DEATH OF NELSON AND BATTLE OF TRAFALGAR, The Balance, December 24, 1805; Size: Small (Item 919)
    - FAREWELL SPEECH AND JOURNEY TO ELBA, Columbian Centinel, June 22, 1814 (Item 920)
    - ABDICATION LETTER AND WATERLOO BATTLE, Columbian Centinel, August 9, 1815 (Item 921)
    - LAS CASAS AND NAPOLEON, Columbian Centinel, March 18, 1818 (Item 922)
    - AMIENS TREATY, The Balance, May 18, 25, 1802, May 31, June 14, 21, July 5, 12, 1805; Size: Small (Item 923)
  - Simon Bolivar
    - ADDRESS TO INHABITANTS OF CARACAS AND EMANCIPATION OF SLAVES, New York Evening Post, August 22, 1816 (Item 886)
  - Mexican War
    - POLK DECLARES WAR AGAINST MEXICO AND EARLY HOSTILITIES, The Vermont Chronicle, May 20, 1846 (Item 1029)
    - PAREDES DECLARES WAR AGAINST THE UNITED STATES AND EARLY HOSTILITIES, The Daily Union, May 27, 1846 (Item 1030)
    - ENGAGEMENT AT MONTEREY WITH GENERAL ZACHARY TAYLOR AND UNITED STATES FOREIGN RELATIONS COMMITTEE, New York Observer, June 27, 1846 (Item 1031)
    - DETAILED REPORT FROM GENERAL SCOTT'S HEADQUARTERS ON THE SIEGE, CAPTURE, AND OCCUPATION OF THE CAPITAL, MEXICO CITY, BY THE AMERICANS, The Daily National Intelligencer, October 27, 1847 (Item 1060)
  - Toussaint Louverture and the Haitian Revolution
    - NEGRO DEPUTIES IN FRENCH NATIONAL ASSEMBLY, Massachusetts Centinel, March 27, 1790 (Item 406)
    - FIRST MENTION OF BEGINNING OF HAITIAN REVOLUTION, Gazette of the United States, September 21, 1791 (Item 407)
    - LETTER OF JOINT GOVERNORS SONTHONAX AND POLVEREL TO GENET ON SHELLING OF PORT AU PRINCE, National Gazette, June 12, 1793 (Item 408)
      Includes French Revolution 951
    - DESTRUCTION OF CAPE FRANCOIS AND REFUGEES, Gazette of the United States, July 10, 27, 1793 (Item 409)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 177 (July 10), Alexander Hamilton 185 (July 27)
    - DESTRUCTION OF CAPE FRANCOIS AND REFUGEES, American Daily Advertiser, July 19, 29, 1793 (Item 410)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 180 (July 19) and Alexander Hamilton 186 (July 29)
    - DESTRUCTION OF CAPE FRANCOIS AND REFUGEES, Columbian Centinel, July 20, 24, 1793 (Item 411)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 182 (July 20) and Alexander Hamilton 183 (July 24)
    - PROCLAMATION OF COMMISSIONER SONTHONAX, Gazette of the United States, July 27, 1793 (Item 412)
      Any slave who fights for French republic would be free and a citizen of France.
      See: Alexander Hamilton 185
    - ADAMS' PROCLAMATION ON TRADE WITH SANTO DOMINGO (HAITI), J. Russell's Gazette, July 8, 1799 (Item 413)
      First recognition of any black government.
    - ADAMS' STATE OF UNION REFERS TO HAITIAN COMMERCIAL TREATY, Farmer's Museum, December 16, 1799 (Item 414)
      See: John Adams 23
    - ADAMS' PROCLAMATION ON TRADE WITH SANTO DOMINGO (HAITI), Connecticut Courant, May 26, 1800 (Item 415)
      See: John Adams 25
    - ONE OF THE EARLIEST MENTIONS OF DECLARATION OF HAITIAN INDEPENDENCE AND THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A NEW CONSTITUTION BY TOUSSAINT, New England Palladium, August 14, 1801 (Item 416)
    - ADDRESS BY TOUSSAINT AND HAITIAN CONSTITUTION, New England Palladium, August 18, 1801 (Item 417)
    - TOUSSAINT AS GOVERNOR FOR LIFE AND CONSTITUTION, Columbian Centinel, August 19, 1801 (Item 418)
    - EXCERPTS FROM HAITIAN CONSTITUTION, New England Palladium, August 21, 1801 (Item 419)
    - DETAILS FROM HAITIAN CONSTITUTION, Columbian Centinel, August 22, 1801 (Item 420)
    - TWO ADDRESSES BY TOUSSAINT TO NATIONAL ASSEMBLY AND CIVIL AND MILITARY OFFICERS, The Federal Spy, November 10, 1801 (Item 421)
    - ADDRESS BY TOUSSAINT TO THE PEOPLE, New York Evening Post, February 4, 1802 (Item 422)
    - ADDRESS BY TOUSSAINT TO THE PEOPLE, Aurora, February 5, 1802 (Item 423)
    - ADDRESS BY TOUSSAINT TO THE PEOPLE, Columbian Centinel, February 17, 1802 (Item 424)
    - PROCLAMATIONS BY NAPOLEON AND GENERAL BOUDEA, New England Palladium, March 16, 1802 (Item 425)
      Proof of his treachery regarding the restoration of slavery.
      Includes Napoleon Bonaparte 888
    - PROCLAMATION BY GENERAL LECLERC REGARDING TOUSSAINT AND DESSALINES, New York Evening Post, March 24, 1802 (Item 426)
    - TOUSSAINT SURRENDER AND CAPTURE, The Balance, June 1, 8, 1802; Size: Small (Item 427)
    - TOUSSAINT SURRENDER AND CAPTURE, Columbian Centinel, June 26, July 3, 1802 (Item 428)
      Includes Toussaint Louverture 431. 3 copies (June 26), 2 copies (July 3)
    - TOUSSAINT DEPORTATION AND DESTINED TO OCCUPY DUNGEON AT BESCANON, The Balance, June 29, 1802; Size: Small (Item 429)
    - TOUSSAINT ARREST AND DEPORTATION AND LECLERC PROCLAMATION ON ARREST, The Balance, June 29, 1802; Size: Small (Item 430)
    - NAPOLEON STATE OF UNION ADDRESS IN WHAT IS PROBABLY ONLY TIME HE MENTIONS TOUSSAINT BY NAME, Columbian Centinel, July 3, 1802 (Item 431)
    - LAW FOR RE-ESTABLISHING SLAVERY IN FRENCH COLONIES, The Balance, July 13, 1802; Size: Small (Item 432)
      Proof of Napoleon's treachery regarding slavery.
    - PROCLAMATION BY GENERAL LECLERC, New York Herald, September 22, 1802 (Item 433)
    - TOUSSAINT SURRENDER AND CAPTURE, New York Herald, September 25, 1802 (Item 434)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, New York Herald, October 2, 1802 (Item 435)
    - TOUSSAINT IN PARIS IN A STATE OF ARREST, Farmer's Museum, October 5, 1802 (Item 436)
    - TOUSSAINT DEPORTATION AND DESTINED TO OCCUPY DUNGEON AT BESCANON, Farmer's Museum, October 12, 1802 (Item 437)
    - LETTERS BY DESSALINES AND GENERAL LECLERC, New York Herald, October 13, 1802 (Item 438)
    - PROCLAMATION BY GENERAL LECLERC, New York Herald, October 16, 1802 (Item 439)
    - LETTERS BY DESSALINES AND GENERAL LECLERC ON ARREST AND TRIAL OF GENERAL BELLAIR, Massachusetts Spy, October 20, 1802 (Item 440)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, Boston Gazette, November 25, 29, December 2, 6, 9, 1802 (Item 441)
      See: Thomas Paine 507 (November 25), Anti-Paine 525 (November 29), Thomas Paine 509 (December 2), Thomas Paine 511 (December 9). Excludes December 6.
    - TOUSSAINT ARREST AND DEPORTATION AND LECLERC PROCLAMATION ON ARREST, Farmer's Museum, November 30, 1802 (Item 442)
      See: Thomas Paine 508
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, March 30, April 20, 27, June 22, September 28, November 16, 23, 30, December 7, 21, 1802, March 29, May 17, 24, June 14, 1803; Size: Small (Item 443)
  - Mark Twain
    - LETTER FROM MARK TWAIN ON BOARD STEAMER RETURNING FROM SANDWICH ISLANDS, Sacramento Daily Union, February 27, 1867 (Item 1010)
    - LETTER FROM MARK TWAIN ON STEED HE RODE IN THE HOLY LAND, Union Democrat, March 17, 1868 (Item 1011)
    - MARK TWAIN ON JEFF THOMPSON, SIGNED SAMUEL L. CLEMENT, Evansville Daily Journal, April 29, 1874 (Item 1012)
    - ADDRESS FROM MARK TWAIN CONCERNING HIS VIEWS ON THE POLITICAL FIELD, Worcester Evening Gazette, October 6, 1876 (Item 1013)
    - THE PRIVATE HISTORY OF A CAMPAIGN THAT FAILED, The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, December 1885; Size: Small (Item 1014)
    - A CONNECTICUT YANKEE IN KING ARTHUR'S COURT, The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, November 1889; Size: Small (Item 1015)
    - LETTER FROM MARK TWAIN DECLINING FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE, Springfield Daily Republican, June 29, 1897 (Item 1016)
    - STIRRING TIMES IN AUSTRIA, Harper's New Monthly Magazine, March 1898; Size: Small (Item 1017)
    - CONCERNING THE JEWS, Harper's New Monthly Magazine, September 1899; Size: Small (Item 1018)
    - THE MAN THAT CORRUPTED HADLEYBURG, Harper's Monthly Magazine, December 1899; Size: Small (Item 1019)
    - DOES THE RACE OF MAN LOVE A LORD?, The North American Review, April 1902; Size: Small (Item 1020)
    - A DEFENSE OF GENERAL FUNSTON, The North American Review, May 1902; Size: Small (Item 1021)
    - KING LEOPOLD'S SOLILOQUY, 1905; Size: Small (Item 1022)
    - THE CZAR'S SOLILOQUY, The North American Review, March 1905; Size: Small (Item 1023)
    - CHAPTER FROM MY AUTOBIOGRAPHY II, The North American Review, September 21, 1906; Size: Small (Item 1024)
    - EXTRACT FROM CAPTAIN STORMFIELD'S VISIT TO HEAVEN, PART 1, Harper's Monthly Magazine, December 1907; Size: Small (Item 1025)
    - EXTRACT FROM CAPTAIN STORMFIELD'S VISIT TO HEAVEN, PART 2, Harper's Monthly Magazine, January 1908; Size: Small (Item 1026)
- 17th Century Individuals -- English Civil War, Protectorate, Restoration, Glorious Revolution
  - Oliver Cromwell
    - OLIVER CROMWELL LETTER ON DEFEAT OF SCOTTISH ARMY AT BATTLE OF PRESTON, 1648; Size: Small (Item 924)
      Yorktown of English Civil War, leading to execution of Charles I and maybe first defeat of monarch by citizen army.
    - OLIVER CROMWELL LETTER AND INCARCERATION OF CHARLES I, Moderate Intelligencer, November 9, 1648 - November 16, 1648; Size: Small (Item 925)
      Pre-newspaper newsbook.
    - OLIVER CROMWELL LETTER ON BATTLE OF WORCESTER, 1651; Size: Small (Item 926)
      Sending Charles ll into exile ending English Civil War.
  - Richard Cromwell